# 大家好 今天去拔點那個竹笋
Hi everyone. Today we're gonna pick some, you know, some bamboo shoots.
# 你看 這個竹笋
Look! The bamboo shoots
# 像這 這邊竹林里面好多的哦 這個
There are a lot in the, like, the bamboo forest over there.
# 但是都不知道有沒有
But I don't know if there are still any.
# 沒去看
I didn't check.
# 你看 這好密啊 這個竹子
Look! It's really dense, the bamboo.
# 竹子都長到田裡面來啦
The bamboos are already growing onto the farm.
# 要拔掉一些 不要 不要那麼多
I need to clear some of them. I, I don't need so many.
# 這個 搞個嫩的來
Well, let me get the younger ones.
# 老的就
And the old ones,
# 老的就不要啦
I don't want the old ones,
# 小的也不要 挑大的
nor the small ones. I want the big ones.
# 你看
Look!
# 這個
It's ah...
# 這個就嫩一點 這個
This one is younger, this one.
# 這都是長高啦
It's already rather tall now.
# 這個也可以吃的 這個 你看
This one is also edible. This one, look!
# 一搞就碎掉啦 可以的
You can crush it by hands. It's edible.
# 還不老的
And it's not old.
# 好多哇
A lot!
# 這裡好多 這裡
Here are a lot, here.
# 這個小的也不放過
I'm not not forgoing any, not even the small ones.
# 好多哇 這個
Really a lot!
# 都沒人吃
Nobody wants them.
# 不是沒人吃
Ah no! I mean,
# 長太多啦 吃不完
there are just too many. It's impossible to finish them.
# 你看 這個 好肥
Look! This is, so fat!
# 哎呀
Aya!
# 剝開來看一下
Let me peel it and have a look inside.
# 這個肉 (註︰這個「肉」字沒有很好的翻譯，所以改一下用字，表達到讚嘆就行了)
Marvelous!
# 看上去都
It looks really,
# 看上去 好吃
it looks really, tasty.
# 哦 就這一點點
Oh! So just a tiny little bit.
# 吃的話就吃這麼一點點
the edible part is just a tiny little bit here.
# 哎呀 這裡一個
Aya! Here's one.
# 你看 這個 這個超大吧 這個不要啦
Look! This is, this is oversized, isn't it? I don't want it.
# 這邊
And here,
# 好多
a lot!
# 超大的就不要
I don't want the oversized ones.
# 這個要拔掉一些
Some of these shoots need to be cleared.
# 如果不拔掉的話
The bamboo would be too dense,
# 這竹子太密啦
if we don't clear some of the shoots.
# 它會死掉的
They can't survive.
# 這竹子都會死的
What's more, the bamboo would die,
# 和竹笋
together with the shoots.
# 你看 有3個
Look! Here are three.
# 這兩個
And these two...
# 越講越多啊
There are more to come.
# 好多哇
A lot!
# 你看 搞了幾分鐘就搞了桶啦
Look! I now have a whole bucket in just a couple of minutes.
# 這個 這個笋
This, this shoot,
# 還沒老 你看 一折就斷掉
is still young. Look! It can be broken easily.
# 說明還很嫩的
It means that it's still very young.
# 好啦 不要啦
Alright! It's enough.
# 那麼多 都吃不完
So many here. I don't think I can finish them.
# 回去送點給 送點給老人家吃
I'll give some, give some to the elderly.
# 這個是前兩天掰得這個竹笋
These are the bamboo shoots that we picked a couple of days ago.
# 我們用來
We're gonna,
# 烤一下
grill them.
# 搞嫩的來
Let me pick the younger ones.
# 搞個3條
I'll pick three.
# 3條就行啦
Three would be enough for us.
# 先過一下水
It needs to be boiled in the water first.
# 這個笋沒有過水的哦
The bamboo shoots would taste a bit astringent,
# 不過水的話就
a bit astringent,
# 會有點澀澀的
if they're not boiled in the water first.
# 搞3條
Let's have three.
# 這一下水 這個
Boil them in the water, well.
# 蓋著它就好
Cover it, and wait.
# 那只狗 下雨啦
The dog... It's raining now.
# 給它披了一個雨衣
So I've given her a raincoat.
# 這樣就不會淋 淋濕
Then she won't, she won't get wet,
# 淋濕身上
all over the body.
# 呵 這 這個胖了好多哇 現在
Ho! The, the dog is getting much fatter now.
# 走
Let's go!
# 哇 熟啦 熟啦 熟啦 熟啦
Wa! Alright, alright, alright, alright!
# 這個笋 拿過來就行啦
So I'll put the bamboo shoots here.
# 可以 我把它用鍚紙把它裹起來
Alright! I'm gonna, wrap it, wrap it up with foil.
# 把它壓扁就後把它
I press it first, and then,
# 就這樣
I mean,
# 把它分成幾份
tear it into pieces.
# 可以 可以
Alright! Alright!
# 我拿鍚紙來 把它裹起來
I'll fetch the foil, and wrap them up.
# 把這個鍚紙
The foil,
# 竹笋 這樣子
and the bamboo shoots. Put them here.
# 放著 然後再來
Place them well, and then,
# 烤一烤 烤一下 肯定很好吃
grill them, grill them. It must be very tasty.
# 搞點辣椒醬去
Let me put some chilli sauce.
# 哎喲
Ayo!
# 這樣就
That's it!
# 看上去就有食欲
It looks really appetizing!
# 就是不知道辣不辣
But I wonder if it's spicy enough.
# 搞點辣椒油 (註︰其實這只是辣椒醬肉的汁，但不知怎麼譯)
Put some capsicol.
# 好啦 就這樣烤
Alright! We can grill it now.
# 烤出來肯定很好吃
It must be really tasty.
# 這樣可以啦
So everything is ready now.
# 這樣搖一下它
Let me roll it here.
# 那個
So that,
# 辣椒 辣椒就比較均勻
the chilli, the chilli can be more evenly spread.
# 辣醬啊 就比較均勻
I mean the chilli sauce, can be more evenly spread.
# 搓兩下
So rub it,
# 給它按按摩
and give it a massage.
# 這個烤個十來二十分鐘就夠啦
Grill it for ten to twenty minutes, and it's done.
# 嗯 放在這裡 不用管啦
Um! Put it here. Leave it alone.
# 你看 這個該烤熟啦
Look! It should be alright now.
# 很香哦
It smells so good!
# 我拿到裡面去吃
I'll enjoy it inside.
# 聞起來就好有味道啊
The aroma is rather significant.
# 好香啊
It smells really good!
# 看上去
It looks...
# 好香哦
It smells great!
# 搞快來吃一下
Let me get a piece.
# 好燙 好燙 好燙
Hot, hot hot!
# 嗯 可以
Um! Not bad!
# 很好吃哦
It's really tasty!
# 這個 這個竹笋
The, the bamboo shoots,
# 它這樣做是很好吃的
are really tasty when they're grilled.
# 就是
A bit,
# 少了一點那個
a bit more oil,
# 應該是少了一點油
a bit more oil would make it perfect.
# 很嫩
It's really young.
# 口咬就斷
So crunchy
# 有點辣
It's a bit spicy.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 再吃一個
I'll have one more.
# 搞點辣椒來
Let me fetch some chilli.